<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sushrut Bidwai</title>
    <description>Personal website of Sushrut Bidwai</description>
    <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://sushrutbidwai.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 07:30:47 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 07:30:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 4   Principles of Economics   Microeconomics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/microeconomics-course.png&quot; alt=&quot;Principles of Economics - Microeconomics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-price-system&quot;&gt;The price system&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free markets are governed by the invisible hand of pricing. Free markets consist of very large number of strangers who need to collaborate with each other for their own self interest. How do these large number of stranger collaborate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Price is a signal wrapped up as an incentive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In a free market with lots of participants, everyone wields a small influence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A consumer can decide to buy or not buy a particular good at a given market price.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This effectively means that the consumer values the good &lt;em&gt;less than&lt;/em&gt; the market price.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is a signal to the suppliers to find cheaper ways to produce the same good, driving the price down.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This gives everyone a little bit of influence on price.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;World market is not a story of competition, but it is a story of collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-great-economic-problem&quot;&gt;The great economic problem&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All markets are linked together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/interlinked-markets-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Interlinked markets&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The great economic problem is - How to arrange our limited resources to satisfy as many of our wants as possible?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-to-allocate-resources&quot;&gt;How to allocate resources?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Central Planning
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tried in communist countries.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Resources are allocated by a central figure.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Problems with this approach is there is too much information to be digested by single person or committee.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Markets are too interlinked so it is hard to know 2&lt;sup&gt;nd order effects.&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;There are too few incentives to allocated resources to maximize the outcome.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The pricing system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;information--incentives&quot;&gt;Information &amp;amp; Incentives&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does the price system solve the great economic problem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
Price = Marginal value.
      = Lowest value satisfied demand.
      = Highest value unsatisfied demand.
      = Social opportunity cost.
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/the-price-system.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Price System&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;information-problem&quot;&gt;Information problem&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The market captures all information in a single value - &lt;strong&gt;the price&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you value a good more than the price, you buy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you value good less than the price, you find substitutes which are cheaper.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every single consumer makes these decisions every time they participate in trade.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;These decisions about value and price are not based on some global knowledge, it is based on their own localised knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This incentivises consumers to respond to price changes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Similarly a supplier will also respond to price changes to find cheaper ways to produce a good to meet unsatisfied demand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markets are interlinked in many different ways&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Geographically.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Via substitutes and complement goods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Markets are linked via time, current action affects future supply and demand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Market is like a giant computer. It is continuously evaluating price based on signals from trades&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;speculation&quot;&gt;Speculation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speculation is using your knowledge and information to predict supply and demand in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speculators are moving resources through time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is a resource shortage in one geography, it creates an opportunity to buy at surplus geography and then sell at geographies with shortages. Speculators do this through time. They predict whether price will rise or fall in the future. Based on that they decide to either sell now or sell in the future. Hence profiting from their predictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;effect-of-speculation&quot;&gt;Effect of Speculation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/speculation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Effects of speculation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Speculations keep prices stable over long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;prediction-markets&quot;&gt;Prediction markets&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prices are signals that contain information.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It informs how much a person values that good.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It also informs that a person may have some specific knowledge about future.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Speculators are conveying their info by participating in futures market.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Prediction market - A speculative market designed so that prices can be interpreted as probabilities and used to make predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;is-speculation-a-global-good&quot;&gt;Is speculation a global good?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This is not from the lectures.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often speculators get a bad name as it closely resembles gambling. However speculation is different and helps the world in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speculators, by participating in futures markets such commodity market, help keep prices more stable. When current prices are low, but future prices may be high, speculators are incentivised to buy now and sell when prices rise. By selling in future, they are essentially increasing supply in the future. This reduces the price in future, bringing more buyers and essentially maximizing producer and consumer surplus.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 08:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-4---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-4---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 3   Principles of Economics   Microeconomics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/microeconomics-course.png&quot; alt=&quot;Principles of Economics - Microeconomics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tax-and-subsidy&quot;&gt;Tax and subsidy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;commodity-taxes&quot;&gt;Commodity taxes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is a tax on good.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who pays the tax &lt;em&gt;does not&lt;/em&gt; depend on who writes the check.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who pays the tax does depend on relative elasticities of demand and supply.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Commodity taxation raises revenue and creates lost gains from trade known as dead-weight loss.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;who-pays-commodity-tax&quot;&gt;Who pays commodity tax?&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The more elastic side of the market will pay a smaller share of a tax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Elastic demand means more substitutes available, so consumers can escape paying the tax by buying non-taxed substitutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Elastic supply means that the resources used to product the taxed good can easily be moved to other industries so they can escape the tax.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tax burden is determined by relative elasticity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explanation - when a demand curve is highly elastic tax, essentially a price increase, means quantity demanded falls by a lot. If the supply curve is highly elastic, it means number of trades being made reduces significantly. If supply curve however is very inelastic, it means suppliers need to make trades happen and not allow quantity demanded to fall a lot. This effectively forces them to absorb the tax burden. If both curves have same elasticity, then tax burden will be split 50-50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;deadweight-loss&quot;&gt;Deadweight loss&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deadweight loss is the value of trades not made due to tax.
Deadweight losses are larger the more elastic the &lt;em&gt;demand&lt;/em&gt; curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tax-effects.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tax effect&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;subsidies&quot;&gt;Subsidies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Subsidies are effectively negative taxes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who gets subsidy does not depend on who receive the check.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who benefits depends on relative elasticities of demand and supply.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They are paid by taxpayers and they create inefficient increases in trade known as dead-weight loss.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;wage-subsidy&quot;&gt;Wage subsidy&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minimum wage has similar effect on supply and demand of labour as that of a tax. It reduces supply of jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wage subsidy on the other hand increases demand for labour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explanation - Based on observe effects it can be argued that supply of low cost labour is inelastic, where as demand is more elastic. Low cost labour due to skills gap does not have many choices available. Whereas low paying jobs can be automated using technology, so demand is more elastic. This effectively means that raising minimum wage, equivalent to a tax, affects supply side more adversely and hence is not in favour of workers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 08:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-3---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-3---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 2   Principles of Economics   Microeconomics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/microeconomics-course.png&quot; alt=&quot;Principles of Economics - Microeconomics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elasticity&quot;&gt;Elasticity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A demand curve is elastic when an increase in price reduces the quantity demanded by a lot. (and vice versa). Flatter curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A demand curve is inelastic when an increase in price reduced the quantity demanded by very little. Steeper slope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;determinants-of-elasticity-of-supply&quot;&gt;Determinants of elasticity of supply&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Availability of substitutes
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Goods with many substitutes have more elastic demand curve.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Oil - inelastic as not many substitutes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Brazilian coffee - elastic as many substitutes&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time horizon
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Immediately after price increase consumers may not be able to alter their consumption.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Overtime they may.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Classification of product
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Broader - more likely to not have substitutes hence inelastic demand curves.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Narrow - more likely to have substitutes hence elastic.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nature of good
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Necessities - inelastic&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Luxuries - elastic&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Size of purchase
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Relative to consumers budget.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Low cost product - inelastic demand curve in short term. Coffee cost increase by 50% may lead to only small drop in demand in short term.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;High cost product - elastic demand curve.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;calculating-elasticity-of-demand&quot;&gt;Calculating elasticity of demand&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;elasticity of demand = the % change in quantity demanded / % change in price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;D = %∆Q&lt;sub&gt;demanded / %∆Price&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example
Oil price increased by 10%, quantity demanded dropped by 5%, so
E&lt;sub&gt;D(Oil) = -5/10 = -0.5&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Absolute value of E&lt;sub&gt;D&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Elasticity&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;D &amp;lt; 1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;More inelastic&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;D &amp;gt; 1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;More elastic&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;D = 1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Unit elastic.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;midpoint-formula&quot;&gt;Midpoint formula&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To erase base point bias, we use following modified formula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;D = %∆Q/%∆P = ((∆Q/Avg. Q) * 100)/((∆P/Avg. P) * 100)
                  = ((Q&lt;sub&gt;after - Q&lt;sub&gt;before)/((Q&lt;sub&gt;after + Q&lt;sub&gt;before)/2))/
                  ((P&lt;sub&gt;after - P&lt;sub&gt;before)/((P&lt;sub&gt;after + P&lt;sub&gt;before)/2))&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;revenue&quot;&gt;Revenue&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Revenue = Price * Quantity&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For inelastic demand curve, if price goes up then revenue goes up.
For elastic demand curve, if price goes up then revenue drops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Elastic demand is price sensitive. Small changes in price lead to large changes in quantity demanded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;elasticity-of-supply&quot;&gt;Elasticity of supply&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elasticity of supply is a measure about how responsive the quantity supplied is to price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elastic supply curve means increase in price increases supply by a lot.
Inelastic supply curve means quantity supplied does not vary much with price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;determinants-of-elasticity-of-supply-1&quot;&gt;Determinants of elasticity of supply&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change in per unit costs of production.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If high production requires much higher costs, then inelastic supply curve.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If supply can be scaled easily, then elastic supply curve.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time horizon
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Easier to expand total production capacity then elastic curve.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Expand output only using current production capacity, then inelastic curve.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Input materials
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If input materials do not contribute a large percent of toal supply of those materials, then more elastic supply.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;For example toothpicks require wood. But toothpicks are only a very small consumer of wood supply. So even doubling production of toothpicks will have little impact on price and demand of wood.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Geographic scope of market
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Narrow market - elastic. You can easily increase fuel available in one city.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Broad market - inelastic. Very difficult to increase total fuel supply in the world.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;calculating-elasticity-of-supply&quot;&gt;Calculating elasticity of supply&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elasticity of supply == the % change in supply / the % change in price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;S is generally positive. Whereas E&lt;sub&gt;D is negative. Otherwise similar math.&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;slavery&quot;&gt;Slavery&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Case study for elasticity of demand and supply.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A christian organization tried ending slavery in Sudan by buying slave and freeing them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This pushed more people to be slaved.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Organization buying slaves pushed the price, incentivising slave suppliers to enslave more people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 08:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-2---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-2---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 1 Principles of Economics - Microeconomics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/microeconomics-course.png&quot; alt=&quot;Principles of Economics - Microeconomics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;supply-demand-and-equilibrium&quot;&gt;Supply, Demand, and Equilibrium&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;demand-curve&quot;&gt;Demand curve&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Graphs quantity demanded at various price points. Quantity demanded decreases if price increases, as less consumers are willing to purchase the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;supply-curve&quot;&gt;Supply curve&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Graphs quantity supplied at various price points. Quantity supplied increases if price increases, as more suppliers are willing to supply the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-to-interpret-supply-and-demand-curve&quot;&gt;How to interpret supply and demand curve?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If price of a product decreases, consumers who were buying products which are substitutes, are now buying the product.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If price of a product increases, suppliers who were making other products, are now supplying the product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;supply-and-demand-equilibrium-price-point&quot;&gt;Supply and demand equilibrium price point.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When supply and demand are graphed, equilibrium is where these intersect.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In a free market, market forces are always trying to push the price towards equilibrium.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If price is above equilibrium, there is product surplus as demand &amp;lt; supply. This pushes the price down, towards equilibrium.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If price is below equilibrium, there is product shortage as demand &amp;gt; supply. This pushes the price up, towards the equilibrium.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At equilibrium, total gains from the trade are maximized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demand-supply-equilibrium.png&quot; alt=&quot;Demand and supply equilibrium&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;consumer-surplus&quot;&gt;Consumer surplus&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is &lt;em&gt;profit&lt;/em&gt; made by consumer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is the difference between a maximum price a consumer is willing to pay and purchase price.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;producer-surplus&quot;&gt;Producer surplus&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is &lt;em&gt;profit&lt;/em&gt; made by supplier.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is the difference between minimum price a supplier willing to sell at and sale price.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Assuming that minimum price set by supplier includes some profit margin, this is the extra profit made by supplier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;demand-curve-shifts&quot;&gt;Demand curve shifts&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;demand curve shifts right - greater quantity demanded at &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; given price point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;demand curve shifts left - lesser quantity demanded at &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; given price point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;possible-reasons&quot;&gt;Possible reasons&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Income&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Population&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Price of substitutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Price of complements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expectations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tastes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;income&quot;&gt;Income&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For normal goods demand increases if income increases. e.g computers, phones, pubs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For inferior goods demand decreases if income decreases. e.g fast food.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;population&quot;&gt;Population&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Demand curve shifts with changes in population.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;price-of-substitutes&quot;&gt;Price of substitutes&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Two goods are substitutes if increase in price for one good leads to an increase in demand for the other good. demand(good1) ∝ price(good2)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;price-of-complements&quot;&gt;Price of complements&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Two goods are complements if an increase in the price of one good leads to an decrease in the demand for the other.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fuel and cars are complements. If fuel price increases, demand for cars will decrease.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;expectations&quot;&gt;Expectations&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Future price of a good will shift demand curve for the good right now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;tastes&quot;&gt;Tastes&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seasonal goods, fashion, fads.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remember pet rock!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;supply-curve-shifts&quot;&gt;Supply curve shifts&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supply curve shifts left - quantity supplied at &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; given price decreases.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supply curve shifts right - quantity supplied at &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; given price increases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possible reasons&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technological innovations - can drive down prices and/or increase throughput without adding much more cost increase supply.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Input prices - Cost of raw materials, labour, and other input resources may affect price and supply.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tax and subsidies - Additional taxes will drive up prices and shift supply curve up. Subsidies will drive down prices and will shift supply curve down.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expectations - Future demand and prices will affect current supply.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Opportunity costs - If another market has shifted providing better opportunities for supplier, that will increase cost and will shift supply curve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;equilibrium&quot;&gt;Equilibrium&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Free market maximizes gain from trade at equilibrium quantity and prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does equilibrium work? Absolutely yes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demand-supply-equilibrium.png&quot; alt=&quot;Supply, demand, and equilibrium&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 08:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-1---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-1---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>India</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/goa-sunset.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Goa&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After spending last two years in UK and Germany, I have moved back for good to India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plan for now is to do some consulting, while trying out few ideas and see if anything sticks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 May 2021 12:51:52 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/india</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/india</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Machine Learning</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/machine-learning.png&quot; alt=&quot;Machine Learning&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog will host weekly notes from the course. I will update this post to links with weekly notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/machine-learning---course-notes&quot;&gt;Week 1 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/week-2---machine-learning&quot;&gt;Week 2 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/week-3---machine-learning&quot;&gt;Week 3 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/week-4---machine-learning&quot;&gt;Week 4 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/week-5---machine-learning&quot;&gt;Week 5 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/week-6---machine-learning&quot;&gt;Week 6 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/week-8---machine-learning&quot;&gt;Week 8 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/week-9---machine-learning&quot;&gt;Week 9 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/week-10---machine-learning&quot;&gt;Week 10 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/week-11---machine-learning&quot;&gt;Week 11 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2019 10:22:36 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/machine-learning</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/machine-learning</guid>
        
        <category>course</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 11   Machine Learning</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;machine-learning-application---photo-ocr&quot;&gt;Machine Learning Application - Photo OCR&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;pipeline&quot;&gt;Pipeline&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Detect text&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Character segmentation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Character classification&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Optional) spelling correction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;sliding-window&quot;&gt;Sliding Window&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scan an image step by step to check whether object can be detected in it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Draw boundaries around the detected objects/characters.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Feed these smaller images to the next step.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;character-detection&quot;&gt;Character detection&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Train an algorithm which can detect when an image is a the middle of two adjoining characters.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If it detects image as middle of the two characters, mark it as a boundary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/photo-ocr.png&quot; alt=&quot;Photo OCR&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;artificial-data-synthesis&quot;&gt;Artificial data synthesis&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generate data using off the shelf fonts and other image processing techniques to mimic real world data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use small real world training set, but use image processing techniques, generate more samples.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introduce gaussian noise or distortions to generate more samples.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;You need a low bias classifier, so that adding more samples helps.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you can get more real world data, that might be better use of resources than spending time on artificial data synthesis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;ceiling-analysis--how-to-decide-which-part-of-the-pipeline-to-work-on&quot;&gt;Ceiling Analysis / How to decide which part of the pipeline to work on?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mimic a stage is working at 100% accuracy by using training set, but just using label output at the output of the algorithm.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;So if the label is y=1, then algorithm outputs 1, else outputs 0.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This similar to mocking in classical programming unit testing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Step by step mock out each stage of the pipeline and observer the overall pipeline performance in each step.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the mock stage which is working at 100% efficiency does not change the overall performance by a lot, then that stage is not worth working on immediate priority.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ceiling.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ceiling Analysis&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2019 10:27:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-11---machine-learning</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-11---machine-learning</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 10   Machine Learning</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;large-scale-machine-learning&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Large Scale Machine Learning&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Try out the learning algorithm which much smaller sample size, and see if it suffers from high variance problem when small size is small. Only then having many more samples will help.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;stochastic-gradient-descent&quot;&gt;Stochastic Gradient Descent&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/stochasticgr.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stochastic Gradient Descent&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;mini-batch-gradient-descent&quot;&gt;Mini batch Gradient Descent&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/minibatchgr.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mini batch Gradient descent&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;notes-on-stochastic-and-mini-mini-batch&quot;&gt;Notes on stochastic and mini mini batch&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plot cost averaged over 1000 iterations or similar number.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the curve is steadily decreasing, then algorithm is converging, if not adjust appropriate parameters such as learning rate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can use dynamic learning rate. Where learning rate becomes smaller and smaller as number of iterations increase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;online-learning&quot;&gt;Online Learning&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When new data keeps coming in. Streams of data instead of fixed training set.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Similar to stochastic gradient descent, just that training set is not fixed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;map-reduce&quot;&gt;Map Reduce&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Split data and run steps of an algorithm on separate machines.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Centralized server combines results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2019 07:49:11 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-10---machine-learning</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-10---machine-learning</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 9   Machine Learning</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;anomaly-detection&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Anomaly detection&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;applications&quot;&gt;Applications&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fraud detection in e-commerce&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Manufacturing - help in quality assurance by finding anomalous components.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Monitoring computers in data centers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;algorithm&quot;&gt;Algorithm&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/anomaly-detection.png&quot; alt=&quot;Anomaly Detection Algorithm&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;choosing-parameters&quot;&gt;Choosing parameters&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The algorithms works best if the feature has gaussian distribution.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It will still work if distribution is not gaussian.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Features can be transformed to so that their distribution looks more gaussian.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For example
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Feature x can be transformed using log(x), or log(x + c), or sqrt(x) etc.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do error analysis. If p(x) is similar for normal and anomalous examples, then need to find new features which can improve the algorithm.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose features which take on very small or very large values in the event of an anomaly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;multivariate-gaussian-distribution&quot;&gt;Multivariate gaussian distribution&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Original gaussian&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Multivariate gaussian&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Manually create features to capture anomalies, based on given raw set of features.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Automatically captures correlations between features&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Computationally cheaper&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Expensive to compute, does not scale well with number of features, due to calculating matrix inverse.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Works even in small training set.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Number of training examples has  to be greater than number of features. Should be m &amp;gt; 10n&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-recommender-systems&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt; Recommender systems&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;applications-1&quot;&gt;Applications&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Movie, book recommendations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shopping recommendations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;content-based-recommender-systems&quot;&gt;Content based recommender systems&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Essentially a deviation of linear regression.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We find prediction parameters, θ, for each user in the system.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use above parameters to predict which movies the user will like.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Requires availability of features based on content a movie such as degree of action, romance; which difficult to find in real world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;collaborative-filtering&quot;&gt;Collaborative filtering&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cf-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Collaborative Filtering&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cf-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Collaborative Filtering&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cf-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Collaborative Filtering&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 11:41:37 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-9---machine-learning</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-9---machine-learning</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 4   Science Of Exercise</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/science-of-exercise.png&quot; alt=&quot;Science Of Exercise&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;exercise-in-medicine-and-diseases&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Exercise in Medicine and diseases&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;sedentary-lifestyle&quot;&gt;Sedentary lifestyle.&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leads many diseases cancer, cardio vascular diseases.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sitting is harmful!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inactivity is risk factor for major chronic illnesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Even moderate exercise is great for reducing risk of many illnesses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;diet-exercise-and-weight-control&quot;&gt;Diet, exercise, and weight control.&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Obesity is cause for many diseases.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fat stored in abdominal cavity is far more harmful.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Having a tummy/beer belly is far worse than having fat thighs/hips.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you eat more calories than you burn, then you gain weight.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dieting leads to loss of water weight. Prolonged diet will lead to loss of fat, but also loss of protein.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weight lost due to dieting is regained when stopped, as it reduces metabolic rate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;heart-diseases&quot;&gt;Heart diseases&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heart diseases is most common cause of death - 25% in US.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fat deposits in major arteries, eventually blocking blood causing heart attacks and strokes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;59% of heart diseases causes due to physical inactivity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aerobic exercises will reduce risk of coronary artery blockages by reducing bad cholesterol and increasing good cholesterol.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hypertension leads to stroke, heart diseases, kidney failures.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exercise reduces blood pressure and hyper tension.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;diabetes---type-ii&quot;&gt;Diabetes - Type II&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Caused elevated blood glucose levels or chronic hyperglycemia.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Insulin resistance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Symptoms - excess urination, blurry vision, fatigue, thirst, hunger.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Main causes lack of exercise and obesity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regular exercise will increase insulin sensitivity and lower risk of insulin resistance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exercise will help treat type II Diabetes far, far better than anything else.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;cancer&quot;&gt;Cancer&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Modifiable risk factors for Cancer
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Unhealthy lifestyle - lack of exercise, obesity, poor diet.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Environmental - tobacco, diet, sunlight, infectious diseases&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Alcohol&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regular exercises reduces risk of breat, prostate, and colon cancer - 3 of the top 4 most common cancers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exercise can stop growth of cancer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improves antioxidants which are useful in fighting cancer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lowers body fat which can lead to cancer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reduces certain hormones which cause growth of cancer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exercise also improves quality of life for patient undergoing treatment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;aging&quot;&gt;Aging&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Successful aging relates to maintaining your health to live experience desired quality of life.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stamina - regular aerobic exercise helps maintain stamina in older age.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Loss of muscle mass, sarcopenia, which leads to falls, fractures, loss of mobility can be reduced with regular exercise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Never too late to start exercising.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Osteoporosis - Porous bones, affects lot of women. - low calcium, vitamin D.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weight lifting is important activity to counter Osteoporosis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you are active in younger age, it is important to keep active, as adaptations are reversible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;brain&quot;&gt;Brain&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For healthy Brain
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Active social lifestyle&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Quality sleep&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Stress management&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mental stimulation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Healthy diet&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Regular exercise&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exercise helps with maintaining blood flow to brain, reducing risk of dementia.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Parkinson’s disease - brain stops producing dopamine, losing control of muscle movements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 10:26:24 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-4---science-of-exercise</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-4---science-of-exercise</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
