<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sushrut Bidwai</title>
    <description>Personal website of Sushrut Bidwai</description>
    <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://sushrutbidwai.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2021 03:00:06 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2021 03:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Activism</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/berlin-wall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Berlin Wall Art&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-is-activism-taking-over&quot;&gt;Why is activism taking over?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look around, almost everybody is trying to be an activist. Most fields including but not limited to entrepreneurs, academics, government officials, religious groups are being dominated by activists. Why is this happening and is there anything you can do about it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activism is mostly a zero-sum game&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. In fact zero-sum activism is easiest to get behind. It is a us vs them. As long as you can find simple enough grounds to paint &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt; as evil, and &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt; as the good people, it is extremely easy to bully people into supporting your view. You can see this bullying and how it played out in campaigns like https://internetfreedom.in/campaigns-savetheinternet/ .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why is this happening?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;game-theoretic-perspective&quot;&gt;Game theoretic perspective.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let us say you and X&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; are part of a (online) tribe T.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;X is very motivated by movement Z, which is not related to T.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;X tweets about Z, supporting Z and condemning Y.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Now you three choices - co-opt, ignore, or oppose X.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;co-opt&quot;&gt;Co-opt&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It will enhance your mutual influence with X.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your influence in T is determined by sum total of your influence with each individual member. So supporting X will enhance your influence in T.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It will enhance influence of X in the tribe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;ignore&quot;&gt;Ignore&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can continue to ignore X on Z.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As long as views of X do not become dominant view within your tribe, you are fine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If those views become dominant with T, your returns from T may start diminishing. At the very least you will not be able to greatly enhance your influence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;oppose&quot;&gt;Oppose&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you have far more influence in T compared to X, then you can oppose X.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This will neither enhance nor diminish your influence in T, as long as X does not get further support from members of T.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If X manages to gain even one supporter, then your influence starts decreasing if you can not get supporters as well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If both you and X keep getting supporters, the tribe will eventually split into T1 and T2.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Effectively, you lose your influence by half.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on above information, you can see that your dominant strategy is to co-opt X. This is especially true if you are not very passionate about Z to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me explain why&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is a combination of sequential and simultaneous game.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sequential as you can wait for other people to make move, taking a small risk of losing out on being an early mover.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simultaneous as every member of the tribe can make decisions simultaneously.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;So in this case, if you are a new member of the tribe with very little influence. Your best change of gaining some is by coopting views of X.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In a loosely organised tribe where there is no gate on membership, you can see how supporting X will be very lucrative thing to do for new members.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Especially given that it is a simultaneous game as well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This effectively means almost always X is going to win, unless someone with very high influence is willing to launch motivated opposition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the reason why most tribes become fairly rigid in their views. This is how they create shared myths which are very difficult to see past. Anyone who does not believe in those shared myths is eventually castigated. You can see this any number of close-knit tribes such entrepreneurs, academics, climate activists, political activists, crypto activist, &lt;em&gt;organised&lt;/em&gt; religions, and so on. Essentially any tribe where you can not concretely with hard evidence show something to be right or wrong, you will see this same exact behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So is your only choice available is to co-opt, either immediately or eventually, to support dominant activism within your tribe?
It is possibly the best and easiest choice available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now look at it from perspective of X.
X is someone who has moderate level of influence in T.
X does care about Z to some degree.
X may not be expert on Z.
It is extremely easy for X to gain really high influence in T. Even if they do not care about Z, purely from game theory perspective it is quite difficult to resist being an activist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;if-so-then-why-i-am-still-not-an-activist&quot;&gt;If so, then why I am still not an activist&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mainly because over a period of time these tribes will become more and more extreme. What you think of as extreme, they manage to make it a normal within an enclosed world view. Then there is more activism within that already narrow world and it can only push the tribe as a whole towards extreme end. And that is the biggest worry. It is not that there is activism in the world and it is increasing at an alarming rate, but that over time all activism ends up being extremism which has a net negative impact on the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-do-you-protect-yourself&quot;&gt;How do you protect yourself?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do not go into fields which have become tribal in nature - academics and journalism are the most prominent examples of this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do no rely on having a strong tribal identity. Build individual relationships with people that you need help from. Avoid going to group events once you have say 5-10 people in your network. Especially startup events. Essentially any event with more than 7-8 people is not worth going to anymore.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid doing &lt;em&gt;too much&lt;/em&gt; business with people who are vocal activists. Even if you agree with their activism today, I suggest keeping your risk exposure to them as low as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There are some exceptions to this rule, but generally this rule holds. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Don’t want to use any real names to avoid subtext. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I do have a dominant ethical and moral view which manifests as support for political parties or other social issues. But directionality between cause and effect is ethics to party and not the other way. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 20:42:27 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/activism</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/activism</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 5   Principles of Economics   Microeconomics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/microeconomics-course.png&quot; alt=&quot;Principles of Economics - Microeconomics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;price-ceiling&quot;&gt;Price Ceiling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Price ceiling - Maximum price allowed by law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;effects-of-price-ceiling&quot;&gt;Effects of price ceiling&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shortages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bad quality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lines and search costs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deadweight loss&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Misallocation of resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;shortages&quot;&gt;Shortages&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/price-ceiling.png&quot; alt=&quot;Price Ceiling&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;bad-quality&quot;&gt;Bad Quality&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Main effect of price ceiling is that Q&lt;sub&gt;Demanded &amp;gt; Q&lt;sub&gt;Supplied. Sellers have more customers so&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They can cut quality, cut costs and still able to sell at the same mandated price.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They can provide worse service and still be able to sell.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;lines-and-search-costs&quot;&gt;Lines and search costs&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Price control does not reduce quantity demanded.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consumers outnumber sellers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This incentivises consumers who value a good more to pay bribes to buy it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More consumers than suppliers leads to lines and increase in time cost.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paying in time is wasteful as time is a perishable resource.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/line-costs.png&quot; alt=&quot;Line costs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;deadweight-loss&quot;&gt;Deadweight loss&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to price control, not all profitable trades are made, so  there is a deadweight loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;misallocation-of-resources&quot;&gt;Misallocation of resources&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key benefit of free market and the pricing system is that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We want to ensure that consumers who value a good more can secure supply before consumers who value it less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gold and silver are used in many electrical and electronics manufacturing. It is also used as jewellery.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If government puts a max price on gold, some of the supply that should have gone to electrical and electronics manufacturing goes to jewellery.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Manufacturers can not signal to the market that they value gold more by paying a higher price to secure supplies, as there is a price ceiling.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This leads to shortages in manufacturing and instead allocates resources for jewellery which is not as important area.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Price system ensures that most important and hence most valued consumers of good are last to be affected by shortages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/misallocation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Misallocation of resources&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;rent-controls&quot;&gt;Rent controls&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is a type of a price ceiling.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Makes it difficult to find apartments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Often rent controlled apartments are rented by people who do not need them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creates shortages in supply of apartment buildings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Over time due to fund shortages rent controlled buildings become decrepit, unmaintained, and dangerous. Many rent controlled buildings fall down in Mumbai, killing people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;price-floors&quot;&gt;Price floors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Minimum price allowed by law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;effect-of-price-floors&quot;&gt;Effect of price floors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They create surpluses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lost gains.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wasteful increase in quality.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Misallocation of resources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Floors are less common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;minimum-wage&quot;&gt;Minimum wage&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minimum wage is a type of price floor.
Effects of minimum wage on above mentioned dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;surpluses&quot;&gt;Surpluses&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minimum wage creates surplus of labour, leading to unemployment.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People who may have be willing to work at lesser wage are now unable to find jobs as employers can not pay minimum wage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minimum wage affects&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only small % of workers are paid at minimum wage, less than 5%.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Large increase in the minimum wage will cause serious increase in unemployment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test case&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;US government accidentally increased minimum wage in Puerto Rico, by a lot.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Led to many businesses shutting down and a very high increase in unemployment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Communism = universal price controls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 08:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-5---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-5---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 4   Principles of Economics   Microeconomics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/microeconomics-course.png&quot; alt=&quot;Principles of Economics - Microeconomics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-price-system&quot;&gt;The price system&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free markets are governed by the invisible hand of pricing. Free markets consist of very large number of strangers who need to collaborate with each other for their own self interest. How do these large number of stranger collaborate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Price is a signal wrapped up as an incentive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In a free market with lots of participants, everyone wields a small influence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A consumer can decide to buy or not buy a particular good at a given market price.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This effectively means that the consumer values the good &lt;em&gt;less than&lt;/em&gt; the market price.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is a signal to the suppliers to find cheaper ways to produce the same good, driving the price down.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This gives everyone a little bit of influence on price.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;World market is not a story of competition, but it is a story of collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-great-economic-problem&quot;&gt;The great economic problem&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All markets are linked together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/interlinked-markets-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Interlinked markets&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The great economic problem is - How to arrange our limited resources to satisfy as many of our wants as possible?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-to-allocate-resources&quot;&gt;How to allocate resources?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Central Planning
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tried in communist countries.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Resources are allocated by a central figure.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Problems with this approach is there is too much information to be digested by single person or committee.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Markets are too interlinked so it is hard to know 2&lt;sup&gt;nd order effects.&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;There are too few incentives to allocated resources to maximize the outcome.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The pricing system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;information--incentives&quot;&gt;Information &amp;amp; Incentives&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does the price system solve the great economic problem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
Price = Marginal value.
      = Lowest value satisfied demand.
      = Highest value unsatisfied demand.
      = Social opportunity cost.
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/the-price-system.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Price System&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;information-problem&quot;&gt;Information problem&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The market captures all information in a single value - &lt;strong&gt;the price&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you value a good more than the price, you buy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you value good less than the price, you find substitutes which are cheaper.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every single consumer makes these decisions every time they participate in trade.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;These decisions about value and price are not based on some global knowledge, it is based on their own localised knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This incentivises consumers to respond to price changes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Similarly a supplier will also respond to price changes to find cheaper ways to produce a good to meet unsatisfied demand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markets are interlinked in many different ways&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Geographically.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Via substitutes and complement goods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Markets are linked via time, current action affects future supply and demand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Market is like a giant computer. It is continuously evaluating price based on signals from trades&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;speculation&quot;&gt;Speculation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speculation is using your knowledge and information to predict supply and demand in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speculators are moving resources through time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is a resource shortage in one geography, it creates an opportunity to buy at surplus geography and then sell at geographies with shortages. Speculators do this through time. They predict whether price will rise or fall in the future. Based on that they decide to either sell now or sell in the future. Hence profiting from their predictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;effect-of-speculation&quot;&gt;Effect of Speculation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/speculation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Effects of speculation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Speculations keep prices stable over long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;prediction-markets&quot;&gt;Prediction markets&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prices are signals that contain information.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It informs how much a person values that good.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It also informs that a person may have some specific knowledge about future.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Speculators are conveying their info by participating in futures market.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Prediction market - A speculative market designed so that prices can be interpreted as probabilities and used to make predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;is-speculation-a-global-good&quot;&gt;Is speculation a global good?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This is not from the lectures.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often speculators get a bad name as it closely resembles gambling. However speculation is different and helps the world in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speculators, by participating in futures markets such commodity market, help keep prices more stable. When current prices are low, but future prices may be high, speculators are incentivised to buy now and sell when prices rise. By selling in future, they are essentially increasing supply in the future. This reduces the price in future, bringing more buyers and essentially maximizing producer and consumer surplus.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 08:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-4---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-4---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 3   Principles of Economics   Microeconomics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/microeconomics-course.png&quot; alt=&quot;Principles of Economics - Microeconomics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tax-and-subsidy&quot;&gt;Tax and subsidy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;commodity-taxes&quot;&gt;Commodity taxes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is a tax on good.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who pays the tax &lt;em&gt;does not&lt;/em&gt; depend on who writes the check.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who pays the tax does depend on relative elasticities of demand and supply.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Commodity taxation raises revenue and creates lost gains from trade known as dead-weight loss.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;who-pays-commodity-tax&quot;&gt;Who pays commodity tax?&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The more elastic side of the market will pay a smaller share of a tax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Elastic demand means more substitutes available, so consumers can escape paying the tax by buying non-taxed substitutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Elastic supply means that the resources used to product the taxed good can easily be moved to other industries so they can escape the tax.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tax burden is determined by relative elasticity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explanation - when a demand curve is highly elastic tax, essentially a price increase, means quantity demanded falls by a lot. If the supply curve is highly elastic, it means number of trades being made reduces significantly. If supply curve however is very inelastic, it means suppliers need to make trades happen and not allow quantity demanded to fall a lot. This effectively forces them to absorb the tax burden. If both curves have same elasticity, then tax burden will be split 50-50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;deadweight-loss&quot;&gt;Deadweight loss&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deadweight loss is the value of trades not made due to tax.
Deadweight losses are larger the more elastic the &lt;em&gt;demand&lt;/em&gt; curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tax-effects.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tax effect&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;subsidies&quot;&gt;Subsidies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Subsidies are effectively negative taxes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who gets subsidy does not depend on who receive the check.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who benefits depends on relative elasticities of demand and supply.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They are paid by taxpayers and they create inefficient increases in trade known as dead-weight loss.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;wage-subsidy&quot;&gt;Wage subsidy&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minimum wage has similar effect on supply and demand of labour as that of a tax. It reduces supply of jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wage subsidy on the other hand increases demand for labour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explanation - Based on observe effects it can be argued that supply of low cost labour is inelastic, where as demand is more elastic. Low cost labour due to skills gap does not have many choices available. Whereas low paying jobs can be automated using technology, so demand is more elastic. This effectively means that raising minimum wage, equivalent to a tax, affects supply side more adversely and hence is not in favour of workers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 08:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-3---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-3---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 2   Principles of Economics   Microeconomics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/microeconomics-course.png&quot; alt=&quot;Principles of Economics - Microeconomics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elasticity&quot;&gt;Elasticity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A demand curve is elastic when an increase in price reduces the quantity demanded by a lot. (and vice versa). Flatter curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A demand curve is inelastic when an increase in price reduced the quantity demanded by very little. Steeper slope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;determinants-of-elasticity-of-supply&quot;&gt;Determinants of elasticity of supply&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Availability of substitutes
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Goods with many substitutes have more elastic demand curve.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Oil - inelastic as not many substitutes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Brazilian coffee - elastic as many substitutes&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time horizon
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Immediately after price increase consumers may not be able to alter their consumption.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Overtime they may.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Classification of product
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Broader - more likely to not have substitutes hence inelastic demand curves.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Narrow - more likely to have substitutes hence elastic.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nature of good
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Necessities - inelastic&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Luxuries - elastic&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Size of purchase
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Relative to consumers budget.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Low cost product - inelastic demand curve in short term. Coffee cost increase by 50% may lead to only small drop in demand in short term.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;High cost product - elastic demand curve.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;calculating-elasticity-of-demand&quot;&gt;Calculating elasticity of demand&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;elasticity of demand = the % change in quantity demanded / % change in price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;D = %∆Q&lt;sub&gt;demanded / %∆Price&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example
Oil price increased by 10%, quantity demanded dropped by 5%, so
E&lt;sub&gt;D(Oil) = -5/10 = -0.5&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Absolute value of E&lt;sub&gt;D&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Elasticity&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;D &amp;lt; 1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;More inelastic&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;D &amp;gt; 1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;More elastic&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;D = 1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Unit elastic.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;midpoint-formula&quot;&gt;Midpoint formula&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To erase base point bias, we use following modified formula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;D = %∆Q/%∆P = ((∆Q/Avg. Q) * 100)/((∆P/Avg. P) * 100)
                  = ((Q&lt;sub&gt;after - Q&lt;sub&gt;before)/((Q&lt;sub&gt;after + Q&lt;sub&gt;before)/2))/
                  ((P&lt;sub&gt;after - P&lt;sub&gt;before)/((P&lt;sub&gt;after + P&lt;sub&gt;before)/2))&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;revenue&quot;&gt;Revenue&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Revenue = Price * Quantity&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For inelastic demand curve, if price goes up then revenue goes up.
For elastic demand curve, if price goes up then revenue drops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Elastic demand is price sensitive. Small changes in price lead to large changes in quantity demanded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;elasticity-of-supply&quot;&gt;Elasticity of supply&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elasticity of supply is a measure about how responsive the quantity supplied is to price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elastic supply curve means increase in price increases supply by a lot.
Inelastic supply curve means quantity supplied does not vary much with price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;determinants-of-elasticity-of-supply-1&quot;&gt;Determinants of elasticity of supply&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change in per unit costs of production.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If high production requires much higher costs, then inelastic supply curve.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If supply can be scaled easily, then elastic supply curve.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time horizon
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Easier to expand total production capacity then elastic curve.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Expand output only using current production capacity, then inelastic curve.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Input materials
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If input materials do not contribute a large percent of toal supply of those materials, then more elastic supply.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;For example toothpicks require wood. But toothpicks are only a very small consumer of wood supply. So even doubling production of toothpicks will have little impact on price and demand of wood.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Geographic scope of market
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Narrow market - elastic. You can easily increase fuel available in one city.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Broad market - inelastic. Very difficult to increase total fuel supply in the world.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;calculating-elasticity-of-supply&quot;&gt;Calculating elasticity of supply&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elasticity of supply == the % change in supply / the % change in price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;S is generally positive. Whereas E&lt;sub&gt;D is negative. Otherwise similar math.&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;slavery&quot;&gt;Slavery&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Case study for elasticity of demand and supply.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A christian organization tried ending slavery in Sudan by buying slave and freeing them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This pushed more people to be slaved.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Organization buying slaves pushed the price, incentivising slave suppliers to enslave more people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 08:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-2---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-2---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 1 Principles of Economics - Microeconomics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/microeconomics-course.png&quot; alt=&quot;Principles of Economics - Microeconomics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;supply-demand-and-equilibrium&quot;&gt;Supply, Demand, and Equilibrium&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;demand-curve&quot;&gt;Demand curve&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Graphs quantity demanded at various price points. Quantity demanded decreases if price increases, as less consumers are willing to purchase the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;supply-curve&quot;&gt;Supply curve&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Graphs quantity supplied at various price points. Quantity supplied increases if price increases, as more suppliers are willing to supply the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-to-interpret-supply-and-demand-curve&quot;&gt;How to interpret supply and demand curve?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If price of a product decreases, consumers who were buying products which are substitutes, are now buying the product.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If price of a product increases, suppliers who were making other products, are now supplying the product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;supply-and-demand-equilibrium-price-point&quot;&gt;Supply and demand equilibrium price point.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When supply and demand are graphed, equilibrium is where these intersect.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In a free market, market forces are always trying to push the price towards equilibrium.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If price is above equilibrium, there is product surplus as demand &amp;lt; supply. This pushes the price down, towards equilibrium.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If price is below equilibrium, there is product shortage as demand &amp;gt; supply. This pushes the price up, towards the equilibrium.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At equilibrium, total gains from the trade are maximized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demand-supply-equilibrium.png&quot; alt=&quot;Demand and supply equilibrium&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;consumer-surplus&quot;&gt;Consumer surplus&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is &lt;em&gt;profit&lt;/em&gt; made by consumer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is the difference between a maximum price a consumer is willing to pay and purchase price.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;producer-surplus&quot;&gt;Producer surplus&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is &lt;em&gt;profit&lt;/em&gt; made by supplier.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is the difference between minimum price a supplier willing to sell at and sale price.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Assuming that minimum price set by supplier includes some profit margin, this is the extra profit made by supplier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;demand-curve-shifts&quot;&gt;Demand curve shifts&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;demand curve shifts right - greater quantity demanded at &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; given price point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;demand curve shifts left - lesser quantity demanded at &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; given price point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;possible-reasons&quot;&gt;Possible reasons&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Income&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Population&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Price of substitutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Price of complements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expectations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tastes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;income&quot;&gt;Income&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For normal goods demand increases if income increases. e.g computers, phones, pubs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For inferior goods demand decreases if income decreases. e.g fast food.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;population&quot;&gt;Population&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Demand curve shifts with changes in population.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;price-of-substitutes&quot;&gt;Price of substitutes&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Two goods are substitutes if increase in price for one good leads to an increase in demand for the other good. demand(good1) ∝ price(good2)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;price-of-complements&quot;&gt;Price of complements&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Two goods are complements if an increase in the price of one good leads to an decrease in the demand for the other.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fuel and cars are complements. If fuel price increases, demand for cars will decrease.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;expectations&quot;&gt;Expectations&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Future price of a good will shift demand curve for the good right now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;tastes&quot;&gt;Tastes&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seasonal goods, fashion, fads.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remember pet rock!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;supply-curve-shifts&quot;&gt;Supply curve shifts&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supply curve shifts left - quantity supplied at &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; given price decreases.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supply curve shifts right - quantity supplied at &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; given price increases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possible reasons&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technological innovations - can drive down prices and/or increase throughput without adding much more cost increase supply.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Input prices - Cost of raw materials, labour, and other input resources may affect price and supply.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tax and subsidies - Additional taxes will drive up prices and shift supply curve up. Subsidies will drive down prices and will shift supply curve down.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expectations - Future demand and prices will affect current supply.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Opportunity costs - If another market has shifted providing better opportunities for supplier, that will increase cost and will shift supply curve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;equilibrium&quot;&gt;Equilibrium&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Free market maximizes gain from trade at equilibrium quantity and prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does equilibrium work? Absolutely yes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demand-supply-equilibrium.png&quot; alt=&quot;Supply, demand, and equilibrium&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 08:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-1---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-1---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>India</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/goa-sunset.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Goa&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After spending last two years in UK and Germany, I have moved back for good to India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plan for now is to do some consulting, while trying out few ideas and see if anything sticks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 May 2021 12:51:52 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/india</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/india</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Machine Learning</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/machine-learning.png&quot; alt=&quot;Machine Learning&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog will host weekly notes from the course. I will update this post to links with weekly notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/machine-learning---course-notes&quot;&gt;Week 1 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/week-2---machine-learning&quot;&gt;Week 2 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/week-3---machine-learning&quot;&gt;Week 3 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/week-4---machine-learning&quot;&gt;Week 4 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/week-5---machine-learning&quot;&gt;Week 5 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/week-6---machine-learning&quot;&gt;Week 6 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/week-8---machine-learning&quot;&gt;Week 8 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/week-9---machine-learning&quot;&gt;Week 9 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/week-10---machine-learning&quot;&gt;Week 10 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/week-11---machine-learning&quot;&gt;Week 11 Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2019 10:22:36 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/machine-learning</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/machine-learning</guid>
        
        <category>course</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 11   Machine Learning</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;machine-learning-application---photo-ocr&quot;&gt;Machine Learning Application - Photo OCR&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;pipeline&quot;&gt;Pipeline&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Detect text&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Character segmentation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Character classification&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Optional) spelling correction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;sliding-window&quot;&gt;Sliding Window&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scan an image step by step to check whether object can be detected in it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Draw boundaries around the detected objects/characters.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Feed these smaller images to the next step.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;character-detection&quot;&gt;Character detection&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Train an algorithm which can detect when an image is a the middle of two adjoining characters.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If it detects image as middle of the two characters, mark it as a boundary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/photo-ocr.png&quot; alt=&quot;Photo OCR&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;artificial-data-synthesis&quot;&gt;Artificial data synthesis&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generate data using off the shelf fonts and other image processing techniques to mimic real world data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use small real world training set, but use image processing techniques, generate more samples.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introduce gaussian noise or distortions to generate more samples.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;You need a low bias classifier, so that adding more samples helps.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you can get more real world data, that might be better use of resources than spending time on artificial data synthesis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;ceiling-analysis--how-to-decide-which-part-of-the-pipeline-to-work-on&quot;&gt;Ceiling Analysis / How to decide which part of the pipeline to work on?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mimic a stage is working at 100% accuracy by using training set, but just using label output at the output of the algorithm.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;So if the label is y=1, then algorithm outputs 1, else outputs 0.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This similar to mocking in classical programming unit testing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Step by step mock out each stage of the pipeline and observer the overall pipeline performance in each step.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the mock stage which is working at 100% efficiency does not change the overall performance by a lot, then that stage is not worth working on immediate priority.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ceiling.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ceiling Analysis&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2019 10:27:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-11---machine-learning</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-11---machine-learning</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 10   Machine Learning</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;large-scale-machine-learning&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Large Scale Machine Learning&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Try out the learning algorithm which much smaller sample size, and see if it suffers from high variance problem when small size is small. Only then having many more samples will help.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;stochastic-gradient-descent&quot;&gt;Stochastic Gradient Descent&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/stochasticgr.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stochastic Gradient Descent&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;mini-batch-gradient-descent&quot;&gt;Mini batch Gradient Descent&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/minibatchgr.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mini batch Gradient descent&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;notes-on-stochastic-and-mini-mini-batch&quot;&gt;Notes on stochastic and mini mini batch&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plot cost averaged over 1000 iterations or similar number.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the curve is steadily decreasing, then algorithm is converging, if not adjust appropriate parameters such as learning rate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can use dynamic learning rate. Where learning rate becomes smaller and smaller as number of iterations increase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;online-learning&quot;&gt;Online Learning&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When new data keeps coming in. Streams of data instead of fixed training set.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Similar to stochastic gradient descent, just that training set is not fixed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;map-reduce&quot;&gt;Map Reduce&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Split data and run steps of an algorithm on separate machines.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Centralized server combines results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2019 07:49:11 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-10---machine-learning</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sushrutbidwai.com/week-10---machine-learning</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
