<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sushrut Bidwai</title>
    <description>Personal website of Sushrut Bidwai</description>
    <link>https://sushrutbidwai.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://sushrutbidwai.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 23:39:46 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 23:39:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>She cries</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/she-cries.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;She cries&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She cries.
Because she likes reading,
when it rains.
Even on a beautiful summer day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She cries.
Because tears are more familiar.
Even in a warm embrace of her lover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She cries.
Because happiness feels fleeting.
But sadness will last her a lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She cries.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Nov 2021 09:49:24 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://sushrutbidwai.com/she-cries</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sushrutbidwai.com/she-cries</guid>
        
        <category>poetry</category>
        
        
        <category>poetry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Activism</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/berlin-wall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Berlin Wall Art&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-is-activism-taking-over&quot;&gt;Why is activism taking over?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look around, almost everybody is trying to be an activist. Most fields including but not limited to entrepreneurs, academics, government officials, religious groups are being dominated by activists. Why is this happening and is there anything you can do about it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activism is mostly a zero-sum game&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. In fact zero-sum activism is easiest to get behind. It is a us vs them. As long as you can find simple enough grounds to paint &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt; as evil, and &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt; as the good people, it is extremely easy to bully people into supporting your view. You can see this bullying and how it played out in campaigns like https://internetfreedom.in/campaigns-savetheinternet/ .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why is this happening?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;game-theoretic-perspective&quot;&gt;Game theoretic perspective.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let us say you and X&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; are part of a (online) tribe T.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;X is very motivated by movement Z, which is not related to T.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;X tweets about Z, supporting Z and condemning Y.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Now you three choices - co-opt, ignore, or oppose X.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;co-opt&quot;&gt;Co-opt&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It will enhance your mutual influence with X.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your influence in T is determined by sum total of your influence with each individual member. So supporting X will enhance your influence in T.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It will enhance influence of X in the tribe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;ignore&quot;&gt;Ignore&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can continue to ignore X on Z.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As long as views of X do not become dominant view within your tribe, you are fine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If those views become dominant with T, your returns from T may start diminishing. At the very least you will not be able to greatly enhance your influence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;oppose&quot;&gt;Oppose&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you have far more influence in T compared to X, then you can oppose X.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This will neither enhance nor diminish your influence in T, as long as X does not get further support from members of T.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If X manages to gain even one supporter, then your influence starts decreasing if you can not get supporters as well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If both you and X keep getting supporters, the tribe will eventually split into T1 and T2.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Effectively, you lose your influence by half.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on above information, you can see that your dominant strategy is to co-opt X. This is especially true if you are not very passionate about Z to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me explain why&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is a combination of sequential and simultaneous game.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sequential as you can wait for other people to make move, taking a small risk of losing out on being an early mover.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simultaneous as every member of the tribe can make decisions simultaneously.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;So in this case, if you are a new member of the tribe with very little influence. Your best change of gaining some is by coopting views of X.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In a loosely organised tribe where there is no gate on membership, you can see how supporting X will be very lucrative thing to do for new members.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Especially given that it is a simultaneous game as well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This effectively means almost always X is going to win, unless someone with very high influence is willing to launch motivated opposition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the reason why most tribes become fairly rigid in their views. This is how they create shared myths which are very difficult to see past. Anyone who does not believe in those shared myths is eventually castigated. You can see this any number of close-knit tribes such entrepreneurs, academics, climate activists, political activists, crypto activist, &lt;em&gt;organised&lt;/em&gt; religions, and so on. Essentially any tribe where you can not concretely with hard evidence show something to be right or wrong, you will see this same exact behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So is your only choice available is to co-opt, either immediately or eventually, to support dominant activism within your tribe?
It is possibly the best and easiest choice available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now look at it from perspective of X.
X is someone who has moderate level of influence in T.
X does care about Z to some degree.
X may not be expert on Z.
It is extremely easy for X to gain really high influence in T. Even if they do not care about Z, purely from game theory perspective it is quite difficult to resist being an activist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;if-so-then-why-i-am-still-not-an-activist&quot;&gt;If so, then why I am still not an activist&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mainly because over a period of time these tribes will become more and more extreme. What you think of as extreme, they manage to make it a normal within an enclosed world view. Then there is more activism within that already narrow world and it can only push the tribe as a whole towards extreme end. And that is the biggest worry. It is not that there is activism in the world and it is increasing at an alarming rate, but that over time all activism ends up being extremism which has a net negative impact on the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-do-you-protect-yourself&quot;&gt;How do you protect yourself?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do not go into fields which have become tribal in nature - academics and journalism are the most prominent examples of this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do no rely on having a strong tribal identity. Build individual relationships with people that you need help from. Avoid going to group events once you have say 5-10 people in your network. Especially startup events. Essentially any event with more than 7-8 people is not worth going to anymore.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid doing &lt;em&gt;too much&lt;/em&gt; business with people who are vocal activists. Even if you agree with their activism today, I suggest keeping your risk exposure to them as low as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There are some exceptions to this rule, but generally this rule holds. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Don’t want to use any real names to avoid subtext. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I do have a dominant ethical and moral view which manifests as support for political parties or other social issues. But directionality between cause and effect is ethics to party and not the other way. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 20:42:27 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://sushrutbidwai.com/activism</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sushrutbidwai.com/activism</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 9   Principles of Economics   Microeconomics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/microeconomics-course.png&quot; alt=&quot;Principles of Economics - Microeconomics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;labour-markets&quot;&gt;Labour markets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marginal product of labour&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The increase in a firm’s revenue created by hiring an additional labourer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Declines with more labour.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Firms hire as long as wage &amp;lt; marginal product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/marginal-product.png&quot; alt=&quot;Marginal Product&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;education&quot;&gt;Education&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is education just a signalling tool or does education provide real benefits?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Earnings are co-related with having a college degree, even liberal arts degree.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not finishing a college does not add to future earnings, even if a person leaves college in the last year. This is the basic premise of signalling argument.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Education does provide social contexts, building networks, learning skills which are not taught in a classroom.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;unions&quot;&gt;Unions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Western Europe despite having more unions than United States, has lower wages than the US.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unions raise wages by restricting supply of labour.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unions however are not just about wage negotiating, but general welfare of the workforce which does provide value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;compensating-differential&quot;&gt;Compensating differential&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If two jobs require the same set of skills, then wages at a more fun job will be less than wages at a less fun job.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wage captures not just the skill value of the labour, but also social characteristics of the job.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Example - an optometrist in a remote Australian mining town makes far better wages than in a suburban Melbourne or Sydney.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wage also captures any other benefits derived from the job. If one job has more learning potential compared to another, wage at the job with higher learning will be less.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Typically dangerous jobs have much higher wages than safe jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 08:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://sushrutbidwai.com/week-9---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sushrutbidwai.com/week-9---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 8   Principles of Economics   Microeconomics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/microeconomics-course.png&quot; alt=&quot;Principles of Economics - Microeconomics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;profit-maximization&quot;&gt;Profit maximization&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;costs-and-profit-maximization-under-competition&quot;&gt;Costs and profit maximization under competition&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Profit is the main motivation for firms actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In competitive industry firms maximize profits by choosing price and quantity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competitive firms&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Similar products.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many buyers and sellers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Small number of buyers and sellers tot total.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; sellers - sellers that can entry the marketplace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Competitive market =&amp;gt; No price control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some definitions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Profit = Revenue - Cost&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Revenue = Price * Quantity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Total cost = Fixed cost + Variable cost * Quantity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marginal revenue = Addition to total revenue from selling an additional unit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marginal cost = Addition to total cost from producing an additional unit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Average cost = Total Cost / Quantity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;calculating-profits&quot;&gt;Calculating profits&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/profits.png&quot; alt=&quot;Calculating profits&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Price = minimum of average cost, the firm break evens. Which means all costs, including opportunity costs, are covered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;entry-and-exit&quot;&gt;Entry and exit&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the total demand for a product changes, new firms will enter the market or exit the market. This affects total demand-supply curve for the product based on type of industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three types of industries&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increasing Cost industry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional supply requires more input costs - typical in mining and similar industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/increasing-cost-industries.png&quot; alt=&quot;Increasing Cost Industries&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Constant cost industry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/constant-price.png&quot; alt=&quot;Constant cost industries&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decreasing cost industry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a special case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Typically the specific knowledge acquired has network effects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ready availability of specific knowledge reduces entry cost for firms.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This makes it easier to build same/similar products with lower costs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Industrial clusters which produce same/similar products get created to this network effect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;competition-and-invisible-hand&quot;&gt;competition and invisible hand&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competitive markets&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Balance production costs across firms in an industry so that total industry costs are minimized.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Entry and exit decisions balance production costs across &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; industries so that total value of production is maximized.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Profit distributes resources and labour across industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;elimination-principle&quot;&gt;Elimination principle&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above normal profits are eliminated by entry of new firms. Below normal profits are eliminated by exit of firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;monopoly&quot;&gt;Monopoly&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Market power - Power to raise prices above marginal cost without fear of new competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monopolies have market power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources of market power&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regulations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Economies of scale&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exclusive access to an important input material&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technological innovation - temporary power&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;maximizing-profit-under-monopoly&quot;&gt;Maximizing profit under monopoly&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/monopoly-profit.png&quot; alt=&quot;Monopoly profit&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monopoly firm maximizes profit when marginal revenue = marginal cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;calculating-monopoly-profits&quot;&gt;Calculating monopoly profits&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand =&amp;gt; Price = 100 - 2 * Quantity
Fixed cost =&amp;gt; 50
Marginal cost =&amp;gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This is a linear curve, with a slope of 2)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marginal revenue = 100 - 2 * 2 * Quantity&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(A mathematical shortcut to derive marginal revenue curve when linear demand curve.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a monopoly profit maximizes when marginal revenue = marginal cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence marginal revenue =&amp;gt; 100 - 4 * Quantity = 20&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solving for Quantity =&amp;gt; Quantity = 20&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the profit maximizing quantity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Price at this quantity =&amp;gt; 100 - 2 * 20 = 60&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total profits = Total revenue - Total cost
Total profits = Price * Quantity - (Fixed cost + Marginal cost * quantity)
Total profits = 60 * 20 - (50 + 20 * 20) = 750&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;monopoly-markup&quot;&gt;Monopoly markup&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A monopoly firm can markup price proportional to inelasticity of demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/monopoly-markup.png&quot; alt=&quot;Monopoly markup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cost-and-benefits-of-monopoly&quot;&gt;Cost and benefits of monopoly&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Costs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deadweight loss - trades are not made to higher prices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benefits&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patents tend to incentivise innovation. Without patents fewer drugs will get created.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In industries with high development cost and low marginal cost, will be helped by monopoly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;possible-solutions-to-monopoly&quot;&gt;Possible solutions to monopoly&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Government can buyout patents.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prized/grants for drug discovery.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Price discrimination.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;price-discrimination&quot;&gt;Price discrimination&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Price discrimination - selling same product at different prices to different consumers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consumers segment will have different demand curves. A firm can set different prices based on each segments demand curves. Arbitrage may make it difficult to price discriminate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Price discrimination is common&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Different prices for children and senior citizens for trains, movie halls, and even meals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Special prices for students.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Airlines based on time of booking charge different prices. Weekend prices. Seating classes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;social-welfare-and-price-discrimination&quot;&gt;Social welfare and price discrimination&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the total output increases, price discrimination is good, else it is bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perfect price discrimination is price set for each each individual consumer. No consumer surplus, all gains go to monopolies. No deadweight loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;tying&quot;&gt;Tying&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goods are tied. Printers and ink. Cellphone and service plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Base good is cheap. Tied good is priced at above marginal cost. Printers are cheap, but ink is expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tying tends to increase social welfare. People who print less and hence do not need to buy lot of ink, get to print at lower cost as cost of printer is much lower. People who print more and hence value printing more will pay more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;bundling&quot;&gt;Bundling&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goods are sold together. Cable TV, Microsoft Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each product in a bundle will have a different demand curve. For example some people value Excel more than Word. Others value Powerpoint more than Excel. Due to bundling this variability of different demands get accumulated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand for bundle less variable than demand for each good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zero marginal cost makes it easier to bundle goods together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bundling increases profits as consumer surplus reduces and more trades are made reducing deadweight loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consumer welfare may go up or down depending on elasticity of demands.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 08:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://sushrutbidwai.com/week-8---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sushrutbidwai.com/week-8---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 7   Principles of Economics   Microeconomics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/microeconomics-course.png&quot; alt=&quot;Principles of Economics - Microeconomics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;externalities&quot;&gt;Externalities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Costs of trade&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Private cost - Paid by the consumer or the producer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;External cost - A cost paid by bystanders, by people other than the consumer or the producer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social cost of trade = Private cost + External cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Externalities deal with external cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Market does &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; maximize social surplus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;external-costs&quot;&gt;External Costs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/external-cost.png&quot; alt=&quot;External Cost&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When there are external costs of trade, output should be reduced.
Who bears the cost is irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;solutions&quot;&gt;Solutions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pigouvian Tax
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;For example tax on cigarattes.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tax increases price and reduces output.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If tax can capture external costs, then it can be great way to reduce output.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;external-benefits&quot;&gt;External Benefits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benefits to bystanders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example - Vaccine. They protect not just the consumer of the vaccine, but bystanders whose risk of infection is reduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case of external benefits Social Value &amp;gt; Private Value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pigouvian-subsidy&quot;&gt;Pigouvian Subsidy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In case of external benefits, output should be increased.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One way to achieve that is by subsidies trades.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is known as Pigouvian subsidy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;solutions-to-externalities&quot;&gt;Solutions to Externalities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;command-and-control&quot;&gt;Command and control&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example:
Government imposes strict electricity consumption ceiling on washing machines. But washing machines that use less electricity clean less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This kind of command and control is rarely efficient. Government does not have all the information on how consumers value use of electricity. So if instead government imposes taxes on electricity, each consumer will reduce their own uses based on their individual information. Overall this will lead to lowering electricity consumption and reducing pollution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;coase-theorem&quot;&gt;Coase Theorem&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are bee keepers who rent out their bees for pollination services. This market place works because&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Low transaction cost.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;External benefits can be contained, bees travel less.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Property rights are clear; Bee keeper owns bees, farmer owns the farm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pollution&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unclear external cost. How much? Who and Where?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unclear property rights.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Coase Theorem - If transaction costs are low and property rights are clear, private trade will ensure efficient market equilibrium even in case of externalities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coase theorem suggests that a new market can be created to trade externalities as long as property rights can be defined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tradable allowances and pollution&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To reduce pollution a fixed number of carbon credits are created.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Firms can buy these credits for certain amount.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Firms which can lower carbon footprint at lower cost than cost of credit will do that.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Firms which can not, will continue to pollute by buying unused credits.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;But due to limited supply of carbon credits, least valuable uses of carbon are removed from the system and this reduces pollution more efficiently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;incentives&quot;&gt;Incentives&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case of external benefits, incentivising consumers will increase the total social benefits. For example a flu shot can be subsidised, hence more people get flu shot and this reduces cases of flu per year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 08:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://sushrutbidwai.com/week-7---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sushrutbidwai.com/week-7---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 6   Principles of Economics   Microeconomics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/microeconomics-course.png&quot; alt=&quot;Principles of Economics - Microeconomics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;trade&quot;&gt;Trade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benefits&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trade makes people better off when preferences differ.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Value to buyer &amp;gt; value to seller for a trade to happen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Specialization - boost productivity by creating skilled labour and information networks.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It is not possible to know everything about everything. Specialization reduces amount of knowledge required to succeed.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Developed countries have more combined knowledge than developing countries.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;globalization&quot;&gt;Globalization&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it good?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increases combined world knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Comparative Advantage - The more different we are from each other, the more we benefit from trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/comparitive-advantage.png&quot; alt=&quot;Comparative Advantage&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;opportunity-cost&quot;&gt;Opportunity cost&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time and resources are finite.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You want to maximize your payoff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In two country/person examples, trade makes everyone better off, but in larger examples some may be worse off.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Comparative advantage applies to groups and individuals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diversity is a strength when combined with trade.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tariffs-and-protectionism&quot;&gt;Tariffs and Protectionism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Protectionism - economic policy of restraining trade through tariffs, quotas, or other regulations that burden foreign producer but not domestic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tariff - tax on import.
Quota - Quantity restriction of import.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;international-trade&quot;&gt;International trade&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/international-trade.png&quot; alt=&quot;International Trade&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effects of tariff that influence welfare&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Domestic consumption reduces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Domestic production increases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these reduce welfare because&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Domestic consumption reduces leading to lost gains from trade.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Domestic production increases, leading to use of resources in products where they are not as valued under trade, leading to wasted resources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tariffs&quot;&gt;Tariffs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase price, create deadweight losses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Direct production from low-cost to high-cost.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Distribution of losses&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bad for consumers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good for domestic producers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bad overall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;arguments-against-international-trade&quot;&gt;Arguments against international trade&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;reduces-domestic-jobs&quot;&gt;Reduces domestic jobs&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We pay for imports with exports!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trade moves jobs from import industries to exports.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wages increase on average due to comparative advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Problems do arise when low skilled jobs are lost and labour is not up skilled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;child-labour&quot;&gt;Child labour&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Child labour is a side effect of poverty.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Restraining trade due to child labour will further increase poverty and put more children at risk.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trade however in the long run will increase wealth and reduce child labour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;national-security&quot;&gt;National security&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anything can be considered important for national security.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Key industries at home - Maybe valid for very few industries. But supply chains for those are global and hence still difficult without trade.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cost-of-protectionism&quot;&gt;Cost of protectionism&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/protectionism.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cost of protectionism&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 08:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://sushrutbidwai.com/week-6---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sushrutbidwai.com/week-6---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 5   Principles of Economics   Microeconomics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/microeconomics-course.png&quot; alt=&quot;Principles of Economics - Microeconomics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;price-ceiling&quot;&gt;Price Ceiling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Price ceiling - Maximum price allowed by law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;effects-of-price-ceiling&quot;&gt;Effects of price ceiling&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shortages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bad quality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lines and search costs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deadweight loss&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Misallocation of resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;shortages&quot;&gt;Shortages&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/price-ceiling.png&quot; alt=&quot;Price Ceiling&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;bad-quality&quot;&gt;Bad Quality&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Main effect of price ceiling is that Q&lt;sub&gt;Demanded &amp;gt; Q&lt;sub&gt;Supplied. Sellers have more customers so&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They can cut quality, cut costs and still able to sell at the same mandated price.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They can provide worse service and still be able to sell.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;lines-and-search-costs&quot;&gt;Lines and search costs&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Price control does not reduce quantity demanded.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consumers outnumber sellers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This incentivises consumers who value a good more to pay bribes to buy it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More consumers than suppliers leads to lines and increase in time cost.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paying in time is wasteful as time is a perishable resource.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/line-costs.png&quot; alt=&quot;Line costs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;deadweight-loss&quot;&gt;Deadweight loss&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to price control, not all profitable trades are made, so  there is a deadweight loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;misallocation-of-resources&quot;&gt;Misallocation of resources&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key benefit of free market and the pricing system is that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We want to ensure that consumers who value a good more can secure supply before consumers who value it less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gold and silver are used in many electrical and electronics manufacturing. It is also used as jewellery.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If government puts a max price on gold, some of the supply that should have gone to electrical and electronics manufacturing goes to jewellery.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Manufacturers can not signal to the market that they value gold more by paying a higher price to secure supplies, as there is a price ceiling.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This leads to shortages in manufacturing and instead allocates resources for jewellery which is not as important area.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Price system ensures that most important and hence most valued consumers of good are last to be affected by shortages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/misallocation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Misallocation of resources&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;rent-controls&quot;&gt;Rent controls&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is a type of a price ceiling.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Makes it difficult to find apartments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Often rent controlled apartments are rented by people who do not need them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creates shortages in supply of apartment buildings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Over time due to fund shortages rent controlled buildings become decrepit, unmaintained, and dangerous. Many rent controlled buildings fall down in Mumbai, killing people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;price-floors&quot;&gt;Price floors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Minimum price allowed by law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;effect-of-price-floors&quot;&gt;Effect of price floors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They create surpluses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lost gains.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wasteful increase in quality.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Misallocation of resources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Floors are less common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;minimum-wage&quot;&gt;Minimum wage&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minimum wage is a type of price floor.
Effects of minimum wage on above mentioned dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;surpluses&quot;&gt;Surpluses&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minimum wage creates surplus of labour, leading to unemployment.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People who may have be willing to work at lesser wage are now unable to find jobs as employers can not pay minimum wage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minimum wage affects&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only small % of workers are paid at minimum wage, less than 5%.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Large increase in the minimum wage will cause serious increase in unemployment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test case&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;US government accidentally increased minimum wage in Puerto Rico, by a lot.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Led to many businesses shutting down and a very high increase in unemployment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Communism = universal price controls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 08:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://sushrutbidwai.com/week-5---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sushrutbidwai.com/week-5---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 4   Principles of Economics   Microeconomics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/microeconomics-course.png&quot; alt=&quot;Principles of Economics - Microeconomics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-price-system&quot;&gt;The price system&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free markets are governed by the invisible hand of pricing. Free markets consist of very large number of strangers who need to collaborate with each other for their own self interest. How do these large number of stranger collaborate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Price is a signal wrapped up as an incentive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In a free market with lots of participants, everyone wields a small influence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A consumer can decide to buy or not buy a particular good at a given market price.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This effectively means that the consumer values the good &lt;em&gt;less than&lt;/em&gt; the market price.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is a signal to the suppliers to find cheaper ways to produce the same good, driving the price down.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This gives everyone a little bit of influence on price.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;World market is not a story of competition, but it is a story of collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-great-economic-problem&quot;&gt;The great economic problem&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All markets are linked together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/interlinked-markets-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Interlinked markets&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The great economic problem is - How to arrange our limited resources to satisfy as many of our wants as possible?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-to-allocate-resources&quot;&gt;How to allocate resources?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Central Planning
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tried in communist countries.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Resources are allocated by a central figure.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Problems with this approach is there is too much information to be digested by single person or committee.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Markets are too interlinked so it is hard to know 2&lt;sup&gt;nd order effects.&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;There are too few incentives to allocated resources to maximize the outcome.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The pricing system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;information--incentives&quot;&gt;Information &amp;amp; Incentives&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does the price system solve the great economic problem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
Price = Marginal value.
      = Lowest value satisfied demand.
      = Highest value unsatisfied demand.
      = Social opportunity cost.
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/the-price-system.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Price System&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;information-problem&quot;&gt;Information problem&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The market captures all information in a single value - &lt;strong&gt;the price&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you value a good more than the price, you buy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you value good less than the price, you find substitutes which are cheaper.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every single consumer makes these decisions every time they participate in trade.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;These decisions about value and price are not based on some global knowledge, it is based on their own localised knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This incentivises consumers to respond to price changes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Similarly a supplier will also respond to price changes to find cheaper ways to produce a good to meet unsatisfied demand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markets are interlinked in many different ways&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Geographically.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Via substitutes and complement goods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Markets are linked via time, current action affects future supply and demand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Market is like a giant computer. It is continuously evaluating price based on signals from trades&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;speculation&quot;&gt;Speculation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speculation is using your knowledge and information to predict supply and demand in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speculators are moving resources through time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is a resource shortage in one geography, it creates an opportunity to buy at surplus geography and then sell at geographies with shortages. Speculators do this through time. They predict whether price will rise or fall in the future. Based on that they decide to either sell now or sell in the future. Hence profiting from their predictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;effect-of-speculation&quot;&gt;Effect of Speculation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/speculation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Effects of speculation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Speculations keep prices stable over long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;prediction-markets&quot;&gt;Prediction markets&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prices are signals that contain information.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It informs how much a person values that good.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It also informs that a person may have some specific knowledge about future.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Speculators are conveying their info by participating in futures market.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Prediction market - A speculative market designed so that prices can be interpreted as probabilities and used to make predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;is-speculation-a-global-good&quot;&gt;Is speculation a global good?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This is not from the lectures.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often speculators get a bad name as it closely resembles gambling. However speculation is different and helps the world in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speculators, by participating in futures markets such commodity market, help keep prices more stable. When current prices are low, but future prices may be high, speculators are incentivised to buy now and sell when prices rise. By selling in future, they are essentially increasing supply in the future. This reduces the price in future, bringing more buyers and essentially maximizing producer and consumer surplus.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 08:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://sushrutbidwai.com/week-4---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sushrutbidwai.com/week-4---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 3   Principles of Economics   Microeconomics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/microeconomics-course.png&quot; alt=&quot;Principles of Economics - Microeconomics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tax-and-subsidy&quot;&gt;Tax and subsidy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;commodity-taxes&quot;&gt;Commodity taxes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is a tax on good.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who pays the tax &lt;em&gt;does not&lt;/em&gt; depend on who writes the check.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who pays the tax does depend on relative elasticities of demand and supply.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Commodity taxation raises revenue and creates lost gains from trade known as dead-weight loss.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;who-pays-commodity-tax&quot;&gt;Who pays commodity tax?&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The more elastic side of the market will pay a smaller share of a tax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Elastic demand means more substitutes available, so consumers can escape paying the tax by buying non-taxed substitutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Elastic supply means that the resources used to product the taxed good can easily be moved to other industries so they can escape the tax.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tax burden is determined by relative elasticity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explanation - when a demand curve is highly elastic tax, essentially a price increase, means quantity demanded falls by a lot. If the supply curve is highly elastic, it means number of trades being made reduces significantly. If supply curve however is very inelastic, it means suppliers need to make trades happen and not allow quantity demanded to fall a lot. This effectively forces them to absorb the tax burden. If both curves have same elasticity, then tax burden will be split 50-50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;deadweight-loss&quot;&gt;Deadweight loss&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deadweight loss is the value of trades not made due to tax.
Deadweight losses are larger the more elastic the &lt;em&gt;demand&lt;/em&gt; curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tax-effects.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tax effect&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;subsidies&quot;&gt;Subsidies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Subsidies are effectively negative taxes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who gets subsidy does not depend on who receive the check.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who benefits depends on relative elasticities of demand and supply.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They are paid by taxpayers and they create inefficient increases in trade known as dead-weight loss.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;wage-subsidy&quot;&gt;Wage subsidy&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minimum wage has similar effect on supply and demand of labour as that of a tax. It reduces supply of jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wage subsidy on the other hand increases demand for labour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explanation - Based on observe effects it can be argued that supply of low cost labour is inelastic, where as demand is more elastic. Low cost labour due to skills gap does not have many choices available. Whereas low paying jobs can be automated using technology, so demand is more elastic. This effectively means that raising minimum wage, equivalent to a tax, affects supply side more adversely and hence is not in favour of workers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 08:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://sushrutbidwai.com/week-3---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sushrutbidwai.com/week-3---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week 2   Principles of Economics   Microeconomics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/microeconomics-course.png&quot; alt=&quot;Principles of Economics - Microeconomics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elasticity&quot;&gt;Elasticity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A demand curve is elastic when an increase in price reduces the quantity demanded by a lot. (and vice versa). Flatter curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A demand curve is inelastic when an increase in price reduced the quantity demanded by very little. Steeper slope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;determinants-of-elasticity-of-supply&quot;&gt;Determinants of elasticity of supply&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Availability of substitutes
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Goods with many substitutes have more elastic demand curve.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Oil - inelastic as not many substitutes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Brazilian coffee - elastic as many substitutes&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time horizon
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Immediately after price increase consumers may not be able to alter their consumption.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Overtime they may.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Classification of product
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Broader - more likely to not have substitutes hence inelastic demand curves.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Narrow - more likely to have substitutes hence elastic.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nature of good
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Necessities - inelastic&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Luxuries - elastic&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Size of purchase
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Relative to consumers budget.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Low cost product - inelastic demand curve in short term. Coffee cost increase by 50% may lead to only small drop in demand in short term.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;High cost product - elastic demand curve.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;calculating-elasticity-of-demand&quot;&gt;Calculating elasticity of demand&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;elasticity of demand = the % change in quantity demanded / % change in price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;D = %∆Q&lt;sub&gt;demanded / %∆Price&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example
Oil price increased by 10%, quantity demanded dropped by 5%, so
E&lt;sub&gt;D(Oil) = -5/10 = -0.5&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Absolute value of E&lt;sub&gt;D&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Elasticity&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;D &amp;lt; 1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;More inelastic&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;D &amp;gt; 1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;More elastic&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;D = 1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Unit elastic.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;midpoint-formula&quot;&gt;Midpoint formula&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To erase base point bias, we use following modified formula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;D = %∆Q/%∆P = ((∆Q/Avg. Q) * 100)/((∆P/Avg. P) * 100)
                  = ((Q&lt;sub&gt;after - Q&lt;sub&gt;before)/((Q&lt;sub&gt;after + Q&lt;sub&gt;before)/2))/
                  ((P&lt;sub&gt;after - P&lt;sub&gt;before)/((P&lt;sub&gt;after + P&lt;sub&gt;before)/2))&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;revenue&quot;&gt;Revenue&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Revenue = Price * Quantity&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For inelastic demand curve, if price goes up then revenue goes up.
For elastic demand curve, if price goes up then revenue drops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Elastic demand is price sensitive. Small changes in price lead to large changes in quantity demanded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;elasticity-of-supply&quot;&gt;Elasticity of supply&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elasticity of supply is a measure about how responsive the quantity supplied is to price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elastic supply curve means increase in price increases supply by a lot.
Inelastic supply curve means quantity supplied does not vary much with price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;determinants-of-elasticity-of-supply-1&quot;&gt;Determinants of elasticity of supply&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change in per unit costs of production.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If high production requires much higher costs, then inelastic supply curve.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If supply can be scaled easily, then elastic supply curve.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time horizon
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Easier to expand total production capacity then elastic curve.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Expand output only using current production capacity, then inelastic curve.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Input materials
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If input materials do not contribute a large percent of toal supply of those materials, then more elastic supply.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;For example toothpicks require wood. But toothpicks are only a very small consumer of wood supply. So even doubling production of toothpicks will have little impact on price and demand of wood.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Geographic scope of market
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Narrow market - elastic. You can easily increase fuel available in one city.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Broad market - inelastic. Very difficult to increase total fuel supply in the world.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;calculating-elasticity-of-supply&quot;&gt;Calculating elasticity of supply&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elasticity of supply == the % change in supply / the % change in price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E&lt;sub&gt;S is generally positive. Whereas E&lt;sub&gt;D is negative. Otherwise similar math.&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;slavery&quot;&gt;Slavery&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Case study for elasticity of demand and supply.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A christian organization tried ending slavery in Sudan by buying slave and freeing them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This pushed more people to be slaved.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Organization buying slaves pushed the price, incentivising slave suppliers to enslave more people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 08:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://sushrutbidwai.com/week-2---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sushrutbidwai.com/week-2---principles-of-economics---microeconomics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
